our next
speaker is Kathleen deuso I will let her
introduce herself the floor is
yours you uh so hi my name is Kathleen
derusso and I'm here to discuss some of
the lessons that we've learned when
balancing keyword and semantic search in
these hybrid search use cases
and the theme of my talk is called retro
relevance because I'm not really going
to be talking about New Concepts a lot
of them have been around for years if
not decades they're just ideas that are
still relevant now and maybe they're
coming back into Vogue a little bit and
it wouldn't be a metaphor for retro
without a quick metaphor for fashion
because you know there's some things
that should definitely stay in the past
think powdered
wigs but there's other retro ideas like
bell bottom jeans you know 10 20 years
every every so often they're going to
come back into fashion we're going to
update them we might improve them a
little bit we might put a little new
spin on them Rebrand them with a
different name but they're the same
concept and they work really
well so while semantic search has really
revolutionized how we approach
information retrieval using natural
language processing and semantic intent
there are definitely challenges it's a
new and evolving field and hybrid search
and the tooling surrounding bm25 Tech
search helps us solve a lot of these
challenges and a lot of the tools that
I'll be talking about are like those
bell bottom jeans they're never going to
go out of style they work and they can
help us overcome a lot of those
challenges they can make our search
experiences better and they can save us
time so I'm going to be listing some of
those traditional tools and building
blocks and you know things that have
always worked to make lexical search
better and if you've tuned Tech search
in the past a lot of this is going to be
really familiar might be old hat but if
you're coming into this field New from
data science AI or machine learning some
of these might be new Concepts to
you and uh you know we're going to talk
about the challenges that we face today
with semantic search and you know talk
about how hybrid search really is that
Best of Both Worlds you know highlight
some of those tools in that relevance
toolbx that helps us here and you know
our goal is to make high quality you
know search results as simple and most
importantly low effort as possible you
know none of us really want to go back
to the days of painstakingly tuning
single weights here and there I mean
there's nothing wrong if we do that for
use cases but it's a lot of work so we
want to make search and the application
of things like business rules seamless
and hands off if we can or as hands off
as possible for practitioners and we can
focus on making that semantic search and
that hybrid search even
better uh before I start who am I and
why am I here talking to you uh I'm a
software engineer with years of
application search experience uh you
know I started off in a B2B space where
we did uh mostly lexical search and a
lot of filters and a lot of business
rules on things like electronic part
numbers where one character makes a huge
difference and you know totally
different part numbers might be form fit
function or functional equivalent uh
alternates um and then I worked in the
SAS space where it wasn't a search
company but we used elastic search uh
for really cool use cases like uh
building uh you know backing up SAS data
from Microsoft 365 or G suite and you
know searching that metadata within
specific backup Windows to find that one
email you deleted so really interesting
problems that had a Different Twist than
typical keyword search uh and today I'm
elastic I'm on the search relevance team
here and it's uh you know it's a really
great place to work uh and because of
that and you know the fact that I've
also used elastic search since 24 and
it's uh you know I've always been a big
fan of it um the examples that I'm going
to be using are all from elastic search
uh but a lot of the general concepts
should translate even if you're not
using elastic search even if the
implementations might look a little
different the terminology um things like
that uh quick refresher on text search
um you know this is the text search that
we all know and love you know you're
you're taking text you're translating it
you're parsing it you know you're
turning it into keywords you're
analyzing it you're creating those
inverted document lists and then you
know this is how Tech search has worked
for decades and you know there's tried
and tested algorithms such as uh tfidf
and
bm25 and uh because this is a retro talk
let's start with
tfidf term frequency over inverse
document frequency you know how often
does the term appear in the document how
how often does it return in the
index and you know it was really one of
those first ways to show how important a
keyword in a document or a corpus is and
it was heavily used from 1972 in its
Inception through I don't know the early
2000s but I want to put that in
perspective as far as how old T IDF is
it was introduced the same year of The
Godfather was introduced in
theaters VCRs were introduced that same
year I mean everybody had one and most
of us probably no longer even have one
and pong was an arcade
game uh so then after tfidf we moved to
bm25
1994 you know more advanced improvements
like document length normalization
frequency saturation you know more
accurate than
tfidf and bm25 is so heavily used today
that it's actually a synonym for Tech
search you know when we talk about tech
search a lot of times we just say bm25
search and you know what we meet and
well personally it pains me to think
that the '90s were not 10 years ago
think of the '90s as retro uh you know
bm25 is as old as Forest Gump or you
know when we were collecting beanie
babies is when it was introduced or this
company had this weird idea to start a
bookstore online so uh you know this is
all meant to say that it's been around
for a little
while so all of this technology that's
been around for a while there's a lot of
tools in this lexical search toolbox
that we have when we've used these
algorithms like tfidf and
bm25 you know and at the heart of it is
these analyzers and tokenizers you know
pre-processing our text before we search
and this gives us a ton of functionality
you know you're talking Whit space
tokenization or punctuation handling or
stop word removal which isn't quite
really as used as much today but um you
know it's it's still something that we
used in the past case normalization
stemming
litiz so basically anything where you
have to map custom characters or use
these pre-processed characters before
you tokenize this is the stuff that
these analyzers just shined at and of
course the uh traditional filters field
wastes and boosts you know these filters
over structured data can isolate that
specific content that you want to search
on much more effectively than straightup
text search or even semantic search um
you know for books uh some examples
might be author or genre or publication
date and you know the standard example
for boosts is that titles are probably
going to be more important than
description or metadata but you know
boosts can get really sophisticated you
know think geodistance boosts or
popularity or frequency so there's a lot
of stuff that's you know people have
worked on for decades and it's built
into the search software and it can help
you in this type of uh type of
environment of course there's reranking
uh you know learn to rank strategies are
a huge part of that but also
personalization contextual reranking and
now today we're going into semantic
reranking
um so that's you know again it's an
important tool in the
toolbx synonyms you know for slang for
domain specific jargon and you know
synonyms in particular when you're using
semantic search not all models are going
to handle them well and you know
especially if they're very Niche to like
a specific company or a specific
domain and finally we have business
rules and business is rules Encompass a
huge amount of custom rules but there's
some common use cases that bubble up to
the top here uh for example we might
want to ensure a diverse set of results
maybe we don't want every single result
on our result page to be from the same
company maybe we want a couple results
from a lot of different companies or
maybe we want to run targeted ads that
are based on contextual query results or
other personalization factors and these
business rules might not necessarily be
affected by relevance they actually
might even be contradictory to
relevance but you know it's really
important to combine relevance with
these business rules that you know uh
first of all they're going to pay the
bills and uh you know they might be uh
contractually obligated to do this or or
whatever reason but you know we need to
have these rules on top of you know the
pure relevance that we want to um that
we want to
achieve so uh quick refresher on
semantic search uh we've already gone
through this in a few processes so I'm
going to go through it really quickly
but you know you're going to take these
text strings you're going to translate
them into an embedding model into AR
raise of floating Point numbers or dense
vectors and we're going to search on
them using that approximate neb nearest
neighbor the a&n search or Brute Force
KNN
search um alternately we can use learn
sparse retriever models uh and we can
represent this as a list of tokens and
weights and we can use those to expand
that original text that came in to get
the alternate ways of of using those
words and then at query time your text
queries run through that same embedding
model and you know it's also important
to note that vectors can be used for a
lot of different use cases beyond the
traditional semantic search retrieval
you know they can be used for
personalization or
summarization and it's also important to
note that they don't have to be used for
straightup retrieval you know what about
rescoring or filtering or that semantic
reranking and so on um you know and
reranking is really a huge con concept
right now whether it's uh you know LTR
for bm25 search or that semantic mid or
final reranking it's a huge asset
especially when your models are not
going to return the right answer in the
very top result and it can be really
powerful and really helpful and uh you
know just time for a Shameless plug here
for elastic uh semantic uh reranking is
something that we're actively working on
uh we just launched native ranking
support using cohere and there's a lot
more in the pipeline that's coming uh so
it's something that we're continually
making easier to use and and more built
in and supported as a you know a first
class member of our
search uh but again you know this is
just really more of a summary of uh what
the um you know what the tools
are now semantic search is really cool
in so many ways you know that you know
intent of what you're looking for and
you know returning results that don't
have the keyword that you actually
searched for first few times you use it
it's
magic and you know because of that
there's so many buzzwords right now you
know there's semantic search and Rag and
chat Bots and every single company wants
one and it's going to revolutionize
every business right and uh you know
it's not without some pitfalls you know
it it's great that search is cool again
but if you're developing a Search
application and you've got a legacy text
St stack and you're trying to
incorporate semantic search into this
Tech stack there's definitely some
pitfalls that you need to think about
and these largely fall under three
different categories there's cost
there's features that semantic search
might not do well at yet because you
know again this is new it's evolving and
you know we're working on a lot of these
Solutions but some things it doesn't do
well with yet and then there's also
certain queries that you know again uh
right now semantic search doesn't always
do great with
so let's start with cost cost can be
money or it can be time and you know
time can be latency but it can also be
developer time and you know our time
spending tuning a lot of these
models and you know so what makes
semantic search costly there's the
obvious models aren't cheap you know it
training and fine-tuning your model
takes a lot of time it takes a lot of
effort and it takes money and you know a
lot of companies don't have the
resources nor frankly the desire to do
this but your results are only as good
as the model that you use right so you
might want to license a model that's
already available if you're not using a
free one this also costs money and no
matter where you get your model from
there's going to be memory requirements
and there's going to be compute directly
translates into
dollars and furthermore inference can be
slow so you know you can throw more
Hardware at the problem but you know to
speed up these queries and ingest but
that also translates into
Dollars um but finally there's that
other cost and that's developer
time and you know maybe you're a manager
who's responsible for headcount and
salaries or you're a product owner who
is responsible for you know delivering
as much you know value on your road map
as possible or maybe you're an engineer
like myself who has a finite number of
hours in any given
day you know we don't want to spend our
valuable time on things that can easily
be solved with tools you know it this is
definitely a cost and if you're not
doing things efficiently you may be
spending too much of that valuable time
on the wrong
problems
so why don't we spend that time and save
it to focus on solving those non-trivial
and the hard problems that require that
engineering Focus you know things like
chunking or query understanding you know
things that help with the a lot of these
problems directly impacts
relevance uh so you know you need need
to decide what problems that you want to
spend that engineering time to solve and
we were currently you know and always
continuously working on lowering that
development cost making things easier to
onboard uh making it easier to use
semantic search with minimal setup and
lowering the costs of things like
chunking you know uh now that we were
supporting things like nested documents
and joining those nested passages with
their parent documents so everything is
getting better but as we're you know
that doesn't help us now things that are
on the road Ro map for a month from now
we still need to make those tradeoffs
and figure out how to make those
Solutions in the in the
meantime um as far as features that
people have come to expect and search
Solutions things that you know product
people and uiux people think of as table
stakes in in search you know things like
highlighting uh you know spelling
correction typo tolerance um you know
hodl is a great example is it a typo or
is it you know Reddit GameStop
slang um um you know so these are all of
things that semantic search can struggle
with out of the box today with no
additional refinement but again user
functionality these are just things that
are expected and these are things that
should work today and need to work
today and as far as queries that
semantic search might not do well with
you know we're talking these Niche
queries that require exact matches uh
you know for example these model numbers
uh the example is a usba to USBC
connector uh but you know one character
different and you might get a completely
different model number or other domain
specific jargon or business roles you
know if you want to adjust your
relevance based on popularity or
conversions or even marketing campaigns
it's really hard to do this with
semantic search out of the box um and
query understanding is another huge
problem you know there's some easy use
cases here like conversions and units of
measurements that semantic search
doesn't do great at today but another
great example is negative
so try using semantic search for um a
restaurant that doesn't serve meat now
some lm's chat GPT might do an okay job
of giving you some vegetarian
restaurants but a lot of these models
they're going to say me and they're
going to give you results that serve me
because that's what you asked for so you
know those are the hard problems that we
want to be solving and those are the
problems that you know are coming next
so those are what we want to be focusing
on all right so you know hybrid search
comes to the rescue here you know it's
the Precision and the functionality of
bm25 and it's the semantic understanding
of vector search It's the Best of Both
Worlds in terms of both recall and
relevance but that's a big mouthful so
what do I mean by that so some specific
examples of some cases where you might
not get what you want from bm25 and you
might not get exactly what you want from
Pure semantic search but combine it and
it's really powerful you know think
about real estate where you know I've
got specific filters like an inground
pool or a zip code and uh you know I've
got semantic text uh e-commerce you know
I've got a brand name and a color and
then I've got semantic intent or a movie
where I might know the genre and um you
know an actor but I forgot the
title or job hunting where I know it's
remote and I know the job title but the
skills are much more subjective and they
benefit from that semantic
analysis uh or or finally books again
you've got the genre and you've got a
description and but you know if if
you're looking for the title of the
series um you know sorry about any
spoilers in the last one but the in my
defense the first book is almost as old
as
bm25 um so you know what are all of
these have in common it's that content
that's specific to filter on and then
also something more vague that benefits
from semantic
analysis and you know the phrase hybrid
search is really buzzwordy right now
and you know in some systems where you
know you've got a separate Vector
database and you might have to call
different data stores and combine them
and use services to do this one of the
superpowers of elastic search though is
that all of this can be combined in one
single index and one single search call
so there's a few different ways that we
can do this and when I'm talking about
hybrid surch it might be as simple as a
good old fashioned Boolean query so in
example you know here's an example but
in elastic surch you can have Boolean
queries that combine text search and KN
andn search and text expansion and any
other supported query type that you want
to use and you know if you're using Tech
search today you might already be using
Boolean queries with you know various
tiered relevance Clauses that
accommodate a lot of those business
rules and a lot of these custom things
that match you know rank certain matches
higher than others and you know since
it's a query it can be combined with
things like rescores and reranking and
it's really powerful
it's a super easy way to combine these
text and Vector searches into one single
query um and there's one other thing
that I really want to call out about
this particular example because it's
kind of new in elastic search
812 and uh that's the fact that KN andn
is not just a top level query it's you
know you know or a top level search I
should say it's actually a query so that
it can be nested in to that Boolean
query and you can use it just as any
other query where the K is actually the
size of the query um so it's a really
awesome change it's super powerful and
uh you know the author of that PR
actually happens to be in this room with
me at Hy stack so uh definitely say hi
to her if you uh see her
later um but there's other options as
well so uh you know you can use sub
searches and you can combine multiple
searches and apply a ranking strategy
over these different query results um
you know so in this case you can still
combine every single query that you did
the in the um Boolean example you know
text searches and semantic searches you
could use that text expansion query or
KNN or any other type of search and then
roll them up with this specific
relevance and ranking strategy and uh
this example uses RF which I'm going to
talk a little bit more about
shortly um but it is important to note
that um you know this type of hybrid
search is a really quickly evolving
field um the entire field is evolving to
handle this and make easier and better
appr approaches to do this so in elastic
search in the future we will be
replacing the sub searches idea with
something called retrievers and this is
an easier way of describing these
complex retrieval pipelines uh so this
is uh basically doing the same thing as
the sub searches where you're combining
these standard queries as retrievers and
K&N queries and it's again all rolled up
to use RF to rank the results so while
this isn't available yet hopefully
really soon you'll be able to play with
it
but now you've got your hybrid search
and how do you combine everything into a
single result set and this is a really
hard problem especially when these
scores are virtually guaranteed to be
significantly to be vastly different
depending on how the results were
retrieved you know there's that classic
way using the Boolean query example
where we use uh linear boosts you know
you can apply different boosts to each
individual clause in that larger booly
in query and that's a tried andrue nice
old
technology um but it's finicky it
requires a lot of tuning to get right
and you might never ever get it
perfect uh so if you're using sub
searches or retrievers you can also use
rrf or reciprocal rank Fusion you know
it's published research that combines
these result sets for you um and in fact
my colleague Philip kren did a talk on
rrf specifically at hstack Europe in
September of last year year so the
videoos online it's a great reference um
you know along with a lot of our great
search Labs content if you want to learn
more about RF in particular um but the
power of R RF is that it's easier you
know you don't have to tune you don't
have to do that tuning you just rely on
the algorithm to do it for you magic
right but there's tradeoffs you're going
to have less fine grained control over
those result sets and there's also some
little ux limitations uh some many of
these we're actively working on now
but for today you know if your site
depends on traditional pagination or
pinned documents you can't just plug rrf
as a replacement out of the box and
expect it to work exactly the same as
traditional search does
today um and you know it doesn't take
that bm25 boosting into account and
that's the the tradeoff for um you know
take going away from that fine grained
control so if you're boosting on things
like those business rules or if you have
um you know other other bm25 boosts that
you want you're you're probably not
going to get the results that you want
right out of the box so you know there's
there's really a lot of trade-offs there
um but ultimately the method that you
use really depends on your data your use
case what you need to get out of it and
the time that you want to spend on it
but you know RF is going to continue to
evolve uh you know we're actively
working on adding functionality to it
addressing some of these limitations and
it will continue to improve and it will
be continue to be a much more compelling
solution and a much more compelling
alternative uh but you do have to choose
the best option for your use case and
and know the trade-offs to
both so now you've done the work you've
got that semantic query or better yet
that hybrid query and in it encapsulates
everything that you want including your
business rules now how do you know it's
better you know the most important is
business metrics you know things from
analytics you know clicks or better yet
in e-commerce are they completing
purchases conversion rates are users
spending a decent amount of time reading
the content on your site you know
measuring that user experience that are
gathered through those analytics as
direct proof that your searches if not
providing the results that are correct
at least engaging and useful um and you
know this is probably the best slon way
to measure things like rag where the
results are custom they're subjective
and they're almost guaranteed to change
um you know you can consider going down
the road of user surveys um you know
asking users if they thought the results
were good and bad there's considerations
there are users going to tell the truth
are only users that are unhappy going to
respond um but you know it's important
to thought think about those old school
quantitative ways that measure uh that
you're returning what you
want words are hard the old school ways
that um to measure that you're returning
what you want to you know uh is your
recall good is your Precision good and
you know those uh metrics like mean
average precision and ndcg really help
with
that um and of course the gold standard
is to have that repeatable evaluation
requiring those judgment lists on what's
relevant versus not but these take
different forms and they do require
varying levels of work to create um you
know you could buy a sample set of data
with judgment list but how relevant is
that for your use case um you know you
can mine data from Analytics see what
users are clicking on but that might
inject Some Noise based on click bias or
you know people not necessarily clicking
on exactly the best results um so you
know manually creating those judgment
lists and investing that time it is time
consuming and it can be very
subjective um you know a good way of
proving that manual sub um creation of
these judgment lists is sub is
subjective get three people in a room
and ask them to agree on what the
relevance and what the order of the
results should be you're probably going
to get three different answers each
time um but it does have value and uh
once you have that judgment list though
you know the world is your oyster um you
know you can measure your re relevance
but more importantly you can start using
it in learn to rank algorithms um you
know uh time for another Shameless plug
here but elastic search actually has a
native learn to rank support uh is in
it's currently in Tech preview right now
but um you know we're bringing this
right into the stack and and it's
available to use right out of the
box um so you know this is something
that's probably worth that development
time it's worth that development time
investment um but I did want to talk
about the single biggest trap that
everybody falls into at least once when
you're tuning relevance and that's
tuning for one or maybe even a few pet
queries and you know the ones the ones
that you type in when you test your
search results or maybe your boss types
in when they test the search
results and that first result isn't
great so you know you can change
everything about your relevance
algorithm to try to get that one good
result but how much damage are you going
to do to the rest of your relevance
algorithm to tune for that one or two
pet
queries and you know you know there's
really without those um quantitative
measurements of uh of relevance you
don't even know what damage you're doing
Downstream from
that but we've got some tools for that
so if you remember that pet
query you can still have great results
for that pet query and you don't have to
modify your relevance algorithm and uh
this is through the concept of uh pinned
or promoted documents and you know I
think every if not or maybe most search
providers have this uh type of
functionality but they might use
different verbiage around it um but at
elastic we call these query rules and
essentially it's a way to send in some
type of context let's say it's a user
entered query string but it doesn't have
to be and if it matches some criteria
that we have stored we can configure
specific documents that we want to rank
first second third
Etc and uh you know one of the biggest
use cases of query rules is again this
application of business roles because
sometimes those pet queries are directly
related to relevance you know sometimes
you've got to fix relevance but
sometimes they're not uh for example
maybe you want to promote certain
companies or maybe you've got somebody
who's you know worst case scenario
threatening to pull a deal if if if you
don't fix relevance for when they're
searching for their company name uh or
maybe you want to promote different
content to users based on zip code uh
for example you know I live in New York
if I'm searching for baseball related
content I'm much less likely to engage
in something about Boston Red Sox than I
am about New York Yankees
um you know so there's there's a lot of
use cases here and we can use Query
rules to quotequote fix relevance for
these pet queries um you know with the
disclaimer that you know overall
relevance shouldn't be nitpicky you know
we want to rely on things like models
and uh you know ranking and reranking
and even rrf to get it right but let's
be honest there's always going to be one
or two exceptions to that rule and
that's where you know query rules is
kind of the easy button to just fix it
and get it right move on with our day
and not spend too much of our time on it
um you can go further uh you know you
can go through your head queries and try
to you know make sure that we can
guarantee that good search experience
for the top you know I don't know 100
queries or whatever the the number would
be
um but you know and it's not cheating uh
you know you're just guaranteeing that
you know the users that are doing these
very commonly entered queries are
getting a great search
experience um but like the other benefit
to things like query rules is that you
don't have to be the person that manages
it you can set it up and you know you
can have non-search practitioners maybe
somebody who's running a marketing
campaign they can be responsible for
choosing those documents to
pin so how does this work so elastic
query rules are defined by uh creating
what's called a query rule set it's a
list of one or more rules each rule has
the criteria that must match the rule in
order for the query to be applied and
then the actions that we take on the
rule if it matches uh right now pinned
documents are what's supported but you
know um I'll talk a little bit more
about that in a minute um but you know a
rule can have multiple criteria based on
the metadata that you send in from the
client you might have more uh you know
more data like a user ID or whatever
available in the client that you can
send in for these rules uh so in this
example there's a user query string and
we knew their location so we sent both
of them in the rule uh both of those
criteria would have to be met in order
for that rule to be considered a match
and the action to be
taken um and then to access those rules
at search time you send in that
corresponding rule query that specifies
the metadata that you want to match on
and if you don't have any matches it
just runs that organic query as is and
you know it's it nothing gets
pinned uh we will apply every single
matching rule in the rule set in the
order that it's
specified um and uh you know we'll pin
all of those documents that you want to
come back and you know I'm personally
working on plans to make this feature
generally available and adding an
extending functionality to it uh for
example um you know one thing in the
road map is supporting tokenizers and
analyzers which is going to be really
powerful to match on a lot um you know a
more broad uh set of content um and you
know we're also going to be making it
easier for those non-technical people to
manage query rules as part of campaigns
and um you know in the future I really
want to provide additional actions on
top of just pinning those documents for
example um you know if you're searching
for something that has Sketchers in it
let's pin a brand name or you know uh
rewrite the query to have that brand
name uh so those are things that I uh
you know hope will be coming soon in the
future um and you know that's kind of
where the vision can go is turn that
more into something that can help with
those some of those query understanding
you cases as well as some of those ads
and
campaigns um but if you don't use
elastic search this type of pinned
document uh you know it can be managed
in a lot of different ways uh you know a
lot of search applications already
handle this in some way or the other um
worst case if yours didn't you know you
could manage this with like a CMS that
uh modifies the query before it's sent
into the search engine um but you know I
think that this is becoming a lot easier
to use in administer uh because it is so
powerful to kind of correct some of
those imbalances especially with hybrid
search and you know again we're talking
about that cost Savings in terms of time
again um and now let's talk about
synonyms um you know again that's that
domain specific jargon that's unique to
your business it's not in any current
models um you know one anecdotal example
is um elastic has its own learned uh
sparse encoder or sparse encoder model
uh it's called Elser and when we first
first launched Elser my favorite dog is
a puggle it's a cross between a pug and
a beagle I searched for puggles in Elser
and it did not know that it was part
related to dog and you know this is a
really specific use case I still brought
it up to the team um and my colleagues
had a lot of fun debating on whether a
Puggle was actually a dog um I've got
the mic so I'm going to tell you it's a
dog uh but you know this is a good use
case you know a Sil as it is of a case
where hey the model doesn't have this
data but synonyms can help um you know
and it's in all seriousness synonyms are
a great way of uh you know kind of
translating this domain specific
terminology this slang these alternate
ways of saying a word that might be too
specialized for that model to return
with the relevance that we want um and
in elastic search we used to manage this
in a way that was kind of a pain there
was a lot of manual overhead uh you know
you got create a synonym file you had to
upload it you had to reload
analyzers so we've recently updated this
to use a synonyms API um and you know
it's very similar to query rules where
you create a synonym set you define one
or more synonyms and we've got a crud
API that adds updates removes synonyms
and reloads those analyzers for you so
it's uh pretty easy to use and then you
can update those mappings uh to define a
custom analyzer that uses the synonym
app the nice thing about synonyms being
an analyzer is tying it back to query
rules when we do get around to
supporting analyzers and query rules
synonyms can be supported out of the box
which is uh you know again a really
powerful
functionality um and if you're not using
elastic search again you know synonyms
are one of those tried andrue
Technologies it's been used for years
and I'm pretty sure every Tech search
implementation has some form of
them uh so those are some of the tools
that we have uh but what I really want
you to get out of this talk is that
semantic search doesn't replace bm25
search it's only an enhancement to it
and hybrid search solves a lot of those
problems that are innate to semantic
search making it that Best of Both
Worlds and it really shines so semantic
search really shines when you're talking
those long tail and those torso queries
because in a lot of organizations you've
probably already optimized those head
queries to make sure that the common
queries have the best relevance already
and you know these tools like query
rules and synonyms can help free that
time up and provide the best search
experience possible and you know a lot
of these Concepts and tools have been
around for a long while and you know as
that landscape evolves we're getting
better and better at solving some of
those hard problems and solving some of
those pitfalls with semantic search um
and making it really easier to use
semantic search and hybrid search
through simplification and tooling and
that's only going to continue um you
know but our goal as search
practitioners is to return the best
results possible and our other goal is
to do it as easily as possible with
minimal cost including money or time um
and you know we don't want to waste that
valuable engineering time we want to
spend it solving those hard problems so
remember like bell bottoms retro
relevance is in fashion
again uh and while I still have the mic
I want to mention that a lot of those
hard problems that we're solving you
know elastic search Engineers are
actively working on to bring it into the
stack to make it better you know tooling
and search optimization and semantic
reranking Vector search optimizations
and you know we're really working on
that next generation of search tools and
if that sounds compelling to you we're
hiring we've got some great career
openings uh on our career page including
engineering roles working directly with
Vector search so uh we're happy to talk
with you if uh that's something that you
find interesting thank
[Applause]
you all right we have time for a few
questions are
there any oh make me run all the way
up just now I realized I could beat you
halfway you could have but you didn't I
didn't next time because you're an
engineer great talk thank you very much
appreciate it um this is kind of gonna
be an elastic specific question but one
of the things that we've been really
interested in is RF and
elastics kind of new getting into
LTR um with e-commerce one of the issues
we face is with product variance and not
wanting to kind of show the same
variance of a single product all right
next to each other in search results so
there's a few ways of handling that with
either nested documents um parent child
relationships one thing we've been
interested is in field collapse but
field collapse seems to be kind of
almost behind a little bit it doesn't
have support for RF or for LTR and I'm
curious about the future field collapse
if that's something that will kind of be
supported with these new features or
not uh great question um so I'm going to
be honest I'm not 100% sure of the
product road map with field collapse I
don't know if uh some of my colleagues
are
all right so my colleague Maya uh
answered this in the audience but to
repeat for the people in Zoom thank you
Maya um while this isn't currently
something that we support this type of
feedback is super valuable uh so yeah if
you um you know add an issue to our uh
GitHub repo and we can get some
Community engagement on it and get some
some traction on it that is one great
way of getting it into our attention and
possibly even onto our road map um so
that's a great example you know we also
have a community slack where you know
kind of or discuss forums where you can
kind of bring that type of suggestion to
us um and it would be great if uh you
know if that's something that you'd be
willing to do and I'd love to continue
the conversation
there V
Patel you mentioned earlier in the talk
that embeddings can be used for
personalization and summarization can
you please explain how in two sentences
or less in in two sentences or less they
can't it's not natively supported in
elastic search but um if I'm restricted
to uh two sentences or less I'll
say uh you know use models and use
microservices thanks for the talk um I
think during the query rules section you
mentioned that it currently only
supports pin queries or pin documents
I'm wondering if there's plans to expand
that to like use a custom sort or a
function score or something yeah we're
uh actively talking with product about a
lot of these functionalities um so this
is actually another uh case where if
there's something specific that you
would like this is actually the perfect
time to open issues or engage with us
and discuss because we're actively
talking about what the road map is for
this um so so yeah like if there's uh
specific things for uh uh script scoring
or uh you know re rescoring that you
know would be contextually rule-based
I'd love to hear more about it and maybe
we can even chat a little bit more you
know at this
conference ma in many search scenarios
bm25 search often returns much more
results than semantic search due to the
limitation of performance is there a
lesson learned on how to balance and
merge the
results uh so that depends um because
sometimes when you're using a for
example text expansion it's actually the
opposite where uh you know where you
have a lot of these vectors you're going
to be getting way more of those
results um so as far as merging honestly
like if if if if that's something that's
difficult to tune I think that's one of
the use cases where RF is something you
should definitely experiment with uh
because that should take you know uh
irregardless of score it should take a
lot of that um complexity away and and
you know the ideal for that is that
we're going to be using that we're going
to be merging the results in a much uh
more seamless and much more hands-off
way thanks for the great talk um I'm
stars mcus from open search uh we have
many of the same features of course uh I
just wanted to say since you Shameless
about saying you're hiring uh I'll
mention that a lot of the things you're
talking about are also available in open
source so quirky for example has a rules
engine that's been around for a couple
of years uh and U you know we agree with
you on our our research uh supports
almost everything you said so we're in
complete agreement on lots of things and
there are lots of tools out there that
people can
use all right thank
you gulam sarar have you faced a
situation where LTR or hybrid system
variant shows Improvement in ndcg
performance during model testing but
when that model is put in prod the
engagement based metrics used for ab
tests don't perform well if so how do
you re-evaluate this
variant so I don't think that we're at
that point yet um but we have been doing
a lot of
internal uh you know uh modification and
optimization of hybrid search for use
cases on our site so
you know six months from now we might
have more answers to you know with um
you know specific content from that uh
but you know in the meantime uh what I
can tell you is that we experimented
anecdotally and you know kind of uh
manually creating some of those
judgments with um you know using our
Elser model for for semantic search
using just straight up bm25 Tech search
and we found the best results were using
hybrid search and that's currently
what's merged into our Cod base um but
this uh is I'm not privy to what the
results of the AB testing have been yet
because it's pretty new but it's
something that I hope that the people
that are running that um will be
uploading and will be writing blogs
about to try to share some of their
learnings on our search lab site so
hopefully we'll be getting more you know
Insight onto that at some point in the
future and we have time for one more
question
hey thanks for the talk uh Jonathan free
here from shipped two things one uh we
actually asked you guys to open the
collapse rescore feature and um it
actually is on the road map apparently
now so uh there's a GitHub issue you can
already look at uh the other question I
had is there was a slide where you
mentioned with rrf um that pagination is
not trivial uh what's what's your sort
of approach to that and you know how
would you say someone should go about
paginating in that type of workflow so
the reason that it's not trivial for uh
people who might not be aware is the
fact that like okay let's say you get
your first 10 results and you rank them
and you know it works pretty well right
you get to the second page of results
and maybe something from that second
page of results get re gets reranked by
RF and is now on the first page of
results so things shift around a little
bit unfortunately oh sorry you okay um
unfortunately the only way around that
right now is to um basically always
request and always rerank everything
using RF on the max result window that
you want to display not ideal for
performance uh but I believe that we are
going to be addressing that through
retrievers so hopefully uh pagination
will be better at some point in the near
future all right let's let's than thank
our speaker again and it's time for
lunch good luck find
food
e
e e